Hunt Family Papers, 1841-1903
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Hunt family papers
1841-1903
Hunt Family
MS 80
1 box (.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Physician and suffragist. Papers consists of one box of correspondence, biographical materials, and memorabilia. The papers of Dr. Mary Olive Hunt relate primarily to her medical career and include cards of matriculation and registration in courses of the New England Female Medical College. Elizabeth ("Bessie") Bisbee Hunt's correspondence include letters and notes both personal and professional, from famous and lesser known people.
Mary Olive Hunt, M.D. (1819-1908) graduated from New England Female Medical College in 1866-67 and had an active practice as a physician in Manchester, New Hampshire. Her niece by marriage, Elizabeth ("Bessie") Bisbee Hunt (1844-1919) was born in Derby, Vermont and was a leader in the New Hampshire and national woman suffrage campaign. No additional biographical information is available.
This small collection of Hunt Family Papers consists of one box of correspondence, biographical materials, and memorabilia. The papers of Dr. Mary Olive Hunt relate primarily to her medical career and include cards of matriculation and registration in courses of the New England Female Medical College, 1861-63, and certificates of attendance signed by Dr. Marie E. Zakrzewska and other women professors; licenses to practice in Manchester, New Hampshire; newspaper clippings advertising Dr. Hunt's services as a physician to women, and an article celebrating her as the oldest living doctor holding a license to practice medicine in New Hampshire, 1908. There are also two letters to Dr. Hunt from suffragist Lucy Stone.
Elizabeth ("Bessie") Bisbee Hunt's correspondence include letters and notes written in the 1880s from Oliver Wendell Holmes and Charles Dudley Warner relate to her writings. Letters from Susan B. Anthony, Harriet Stanton Blatch and Julia Ward Howe, written in the years 1897 to 1903 when she was a leader in the New Hampshire woman suffrage campaign, include warm recollections of their work together in the earlier national suffrage battle. There are over twenty long and personal letters from her school friend, Rose Hawthorne Lathrop (daughter of Nathaniel Hawthorne). Most were written from New London and relate to her activities in giving readings before women's clubs, a visit to her brother, Julian Hawthorne, in Jamaica, and a report of the performance of the opera based on The Scarlet letter with words by her husband and music by Walter Damrosch. A few later letters, written after her conversion to the Roman Catholic religion, describe her work for the free hospital for needy incurable cancer patients which she founded in New York City, and of her religious life at Rosemary Hill Home.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Hunt Family Papers were donated to the SSC by Mary Hunt Clough Russell (Smith class 1930), Elizabeth Clough Marston (class 1929), and Constance Clough McWhinney (class 1932), all granddaughters of Elizabeth Bisbee Hunt.
Search Terms
Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906; Blatch, Harriot Stanton, 1856-1940--Correspondence; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894--Correspondence; Howe, Julia Ward, 1819-1910--Correspondence; Lathrop, Rose Hawthorne, 1851-1926; Stone, Lucy, 1818-1893--Correspondence; Warner, Charles Dudley, 1829-1900--Correspondence; Hunt family; Women physicians--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Women--Suffrage--United States--History--Sources
- Dr. Mary Olive Hunt
  - Correspondence
    - Family and friends, 1841, 1857, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lucy Stone, 1871, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical materials
    - Licenses to practice medicine in Manchester, N. H., 1863-65 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - New England Female Medical College: certificates of attendance, letter from Dean Cooke, and article by Hunt, 1843-1863 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Biographical articles, clippings, tax form, 1864-1908, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Elizabeth (Bessie) Bisbee Hunt
  - Correspondence
    - Anthony, Susan B., 1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Blatch, Harriet Stanton, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1890s-1902, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Howe, Julia Ward (includes letter from Howe to Manchester Union on New Hampshire Suffrage Campaign, 1903), 1899, 1903, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      [See also Flat File]
    - Lathrop, Rose Hawthorn (includes 4 letters from others and clippings about Rose Lathrop, 1897-98), 1890s-1902, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Warner, Charles Dudley, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Programs
    - Dr. Lewis' School for Young Ladies, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1st Annual Meeting, NH State Federation of Women's Clubs, 1896 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Julia Ward Howe (Map-case Flat File:)